土星五号把人类首次送上了月球
The Saturn V rocket took humans to the moon for the first time,
但并不是人类控制的火箭转向
but the humans didn't steer the rocket.
而是由火箭自身的计算机控制的
It steered itself using a computer.
土星五号火箭的很多部分是在这里 阿拉巴马州亨茨维尔市制造的
A lot of the Saturn V rocket was built here in Huntsville, Alabama,
著名的火箭城
otherwise known as Rocket City.
住在这最牛逼的一件事是
And one of the really cool things about living here
这附近全都是对这项事业充满热爱的航天、计算机工程师
is it's filled with aerospace and computer engineers who love this stuff,
在这里 你拿起电话 找你的一个朋友
so a thing you can actually do here is pick up the phone and call one of your friends
然后他再找他的一个哥们
and have them call their friend,
然后这个素未相识的哥们就约好和你在停车场见面
and before you know it, you're in a parking lot,
借给你一套土星五号的存储模块
receiving a Saturn V memory module from a guy you just met,
而他也会完全信任你 相信你之后会归还给他
and he just trusts that you're gonna give it back to him.
我手里这是14KB的数据 真的很有意思
This is 14 kilobytes of data, which is really interesting
因为我拿到这个的那天
because the same day I got this,
刚好Linus Tech Tips的老莱也来我这了
I had Linus Sebastian from Linus Tech Tips here.
我们在弄一台超过100T的服务器
We were installing a server that was over 100 terabytes.
如今老莱的频道有上百万人订阅
Now, millions of people look to Linus to understand
学到了越来越多的现代电脑硬件知识
more about modern computing hardware,
所以我突然想放下手里组装服务器的事情
so I thought a really cool thing to do would be stop what we were doing with the server
仔细看看这个存储模块 了解一下它的工作原理
and take a closer look at this memory module and how it works.
我们来看看 现代计算机技术宅是如何看待60年代的尖端科技的吧
Let's sit back and watch a modern computer nerd learn about the cutting edge technology from the 1960s.
我是Destin 让我们进入今天的《SmarterEveryDay》
I'm Destin, let's go get smarter every day.
你见过土星五号吗？
Have you ever seen a Saturn V rocket?
没见过
No.
那你知道土星五号是啥吗？
Okay, do you know what the Saturn V is?
知道
Yes.
我的日常生活就是绕着土星五号转的
My daily life literally revolves around the Saturn V.
为啥呢 你看远处树梢那伸出来的尖
Like, that's the Saturn V peeking out over the trees right there.
啊看到了 哈喽啊
Oh, there it is. Hello.
在六十年代 人们才刚开始制造数字计算机
In the 60s, they had just started building digital computers,
我要带你看 他们当时用来控制火箭转向的计算机
and I'm gonna show you the computer that they used to steer that thing.
我觉得这在当时应该还是挺吓人的感觉
I mean, it's gotta be a bit of a terrifying experience having, like,
屁股底下是一个超大号的炸弹
you know, the equivalent of a very large bomb strapped to your butt.
这就是土星五号火箭的大脑
So this is the brain for the Saturn V rocket.
抬头看这里 这个环里就是控制设备
If you look up right here, this is the instrumentation ring,
上面就是数字计算机
and so they had computers on here that were digital.
这里的是火箭数字计算机（LVDC）
This right here is the launch vehicle digital computer.
就这个
That is it.
这是存储模块
This right here is a memory module, okay?
如果你非常非常仔细看的话
And if you look really, really, really close,
仔细看 看到那些小环了吗？
really close, you see those little bitty rings?
嗯
Yeah.
好 看这里
OK, look right here. Look at that.
看到了没有
Do you see that?
我勒个去！
Holy smokes!
看上去就像铁丝网上的扎带一样
so they're, just like, it looks like zip ties on chicken wire.
这些就代表比特(bit)
Okay, those are bits.
它们是物理比特
Those are physical bits.
你看到这个面板了吧？
So you see that screen?
嗯
Yeah.
这些金属线连接到板子底部
These are wires that go down to these boards right here, right?
嗯
Yeah.
每个节点上都有一个铁环
On each node, you have an iron ring,
而根据每个铁环的磁化方向
and depending on how the iron ring is magnetized,
来代表1或0
that's a one or a zero.
他们就是这样来给计算机编程的
That's how they programmed this computer.
真假？
Seriously.
你看这张图
So look at this right here.
纯手工的？
So by hand.
是的
By hand, yes.
他们把线穿过……
They threaded these wires through the,
这手也太稳了……我感觉……
I mean, who has a steady, I don't even think
放到今天也没谁能做到吧
you can build one of these today if you wanted to.
不敢相信
That's incredible.
这有个人叫Luke 是在60年代搞这个的
So there's a guy that worked on this in the 60s here. His name is Luke.
嗯
Yeah.
你可以问他所有这些问题
And, you get ask him all of these questions.
棒极了
Fantastic.
我叫Luke Talley 在1969年的这时候我是IBM在亨茨维尔的高级副工程师
I'm Luke Talley, and at this time in 1969 I was a senior associate engineer at IBM in Huntsville.
所以您的计算机控制了火箭的转向？
So your computer pointed the rocket?
没错
That's right.
了不起
Awesome.
我们控制了火箭的转向
We steered the rocket.
这是存储模块
So that's a memory module.
嗯 一整个存储模块
That's a whole memory module, yeah.
你俩从哪偷来的这是？
You musta shot somebody to get that.
您觉得这东西有多珍贵？
So how valuable would you say that is?
呃……现在的话……我也说不好
Well, now this, ah, I don't, I'd have no idea.
你得去古董店问问
You have to go to Antique Roadshow.
这个计算机控制所有的时序部分
This computer controls all the timing.
发动机启动 关闭 火箭的分离发动机点火
Start engine, stop engine, fire separation rockets,
反推发动机点火 所有这类的事情
fire retro rockets, all this kinda stuff.
它还负责导航和制导
It does navigation and guidance.
存储里预装有一份发射流程的资料
You have stored in the memory a profile,
在某时某阶段 我要在哪
at this point in time I need to be here,
速度需要有多快 要往哪飞
going this fast, going this direction.
你可以注意到这是磁芯存储器
Now realize that this is core memory,
所以它上面有很多磁芯（磁环）
so you have these magnetic cores,
磁芯中穿有导线
you have the wires feeding through the cores,
导线通电的时候
you push a current down through a wire,
如果导线的电流方向是拇指方向
if you've got a wire, current's going in that direction,
那磁场方向就可以由右手定则判断出来
the magnetic field is going to be in this direction.
电流反过来 磁场就是另一个方向
If it's going this way, it'll be that way.
然后定义一边是1 一边是0
Make that a one, make that a zero.
一个平面上有8192个磁芯
There's 8192 of those on this plane, all right?
嗯
Yeah.
然后构成这样的存储模块需要有14个这样的平面
Then there's 14 of those planes stack up to make this module.
这个模块就是你手里拿着的这款
This module is what you're holding.
现在所有这些东西，要驱动它的时候……
All this stuff now, the drivers to drive this thing.
就用它来编写0或1了？
That's just to program it as a one or a zero.
因为这本质上讲这个过程属于模拟信号
Because this is basically an analog process.
懂了
Right.
我不是往逻辑门里写纯粹的0或1
I'm not writing ones and zeros into a logic gate and storing them that way.
您是在送入电流
You're just sending a current --
我是在让磁芯向某个方向磁化
I'm actually having to make, magnetize a core one way or the other.
然后读取它 而且当我读取的时候
And then I've gotta read it, and when I read it,
我会破坏磁芯的磁化状态
I destroy the magnetization,
所以我要回过头来……
so I have to turn right back around and --
重新再写入？
Write it again.
重新写入进去 防止数据丢失
Write it back in there, so that it's not missing.
不会吧！
Oh, no!
所以现在 你手里有一个模块
So there's one of these in this,
然后这边这面墙上 每一块里都有一个这样的模块
and then there's one of these now in each one of these blocks on this wall over here.
明白了
Got it.
这边有16字的存储
So we have four, 8, 12, 16 thousand words of memory,
另一边也是16字的存储
another four, 8, 12, 16 thousand words of memory.
当土星系列火箭飞行的时候 两边的存储会执行完全相同的飞行程序
Now when the Saturn's flying, both of these memories are executing the same flight program.
完全并行的？
Completely in parallel?
没错 之后它们会对比输出结果
That's right, and they're comparing the outputs
保证得到的结果是相同的
to make sure they're getting the same answer.
如果输出结果不同
If they were to not get the same answer,
就跳转到子程序
go into the sub-routine and say,
大致内容就是我在飞行的某点
"I'm at this point in the flight,
得到的两个结果 哪个结果更合理呢？
I got these two numbers, what makes the most sense to keep using,"
就用那个更合理的继续飞吧！
use that number and keep going.
所以逻辑上的关键部分是三冗余
So your critical parts are triple-redundant in the logic,
存储上是双冗余
dual redundant in the memory.
在我的记忆中 土星系列火箭的所有飞行
As I recall, during all the Saturn flights,
总共只有大概不到10次出现输出结果不匹配的情况
we had like, less than 10 miscompares, something like that.
这已经是很小的数字了
It was a very small number.
当你造火箭的时候
When you're building a rocket,
你需要监看很多重要的参数
you have some important parameters that you have to monitor.
动力 数据带宽 质量 容积
Power, data bandwidth, mass, volume,
你需要对数据做好管理 保证一切不会失控
you have to manage these so they don't get out of control.
所以你需要系统足够可靠
So you want a reliable system,
但这又会带来一个新的决策上的问题
but at some point, you have to make a decision.
多少的冗余才算足够？
How redundant is redundant enough?
关键在于火箭的不可靠性
Unreliability, that's the key,
因为这些东西越多
because the more of these things,
你加入的磁芯越多 你就需要更多的这样的模块
the more core's you add, the more of this stuff you need,
你就会给系统增加更多的不可靠因素
the more unreliability you add to your system,
因为零件的数量太多了
because sheer numbers of parts.
对
Right.
Luke接下来要向大家介绍接收土星五号的遥测数据并对其进行分析的过程
Luke is about to explain what it was like to receive data from the Saturn V via telemetry and then analyze it,
我想给大家看这段 因为我希望大家知道 这件事情在当时有多繁琐多困难
and I'm gonna let this play out, because I want you to understand how repetitive and difficult this task was.
今天我们拿电子表格只要几分钟就统计完了
Today we could do this with just a few minutes and some spreadsheet software,
但在当时那个年代 他们就是人肉计算机
but back in the day, they were the computers.
他们自己就要充当计算机的角色
Like, the people were the computers.
所以我希望大家能从他的口吻 站在历史的角度 从而明白
So I want you to see it through his eyes, through this historical lens so you understand
分析土星五号的数据是怎样的过程
what it was like to analyze the Saturn V data.
火箭在飞的时候您就把数据收集下来了吗？
So did you pull the data down while it was flying?
飞行时间那么短来不及的
Things happen too quick in flight to.
那您是怎么……
How do you know you had --
我们把数据带回来 然后再慢慢分析
We get the data back and then we ana,
我在IBM的职责就是这个
that was my job at IBM,
我们分析飞行数据 找到哪里正常工作了 哪里没有正常工作
was we were analyzing the flight data to determine what worked, what didn't work,
如果这次出问题了 如何修复 保证下次不出问题
if it didn't work on this flight, how do we fix it on the next flight?
懂了
Got it.
然后再下次飞行之前 满足NASA的需求
And then when you get the NASA requirements for the next flight,
保证每样零件都能做到其应该做的
make sure we got everything in place to do what we were supposed to do,
数据磁带是来自全世界各地的
so the data tapes come from all around the world
汇总到戈达德太空飞行中心 他们负责这个
through Goddard Space Flight Center's responsible for that,
他们把数据给我们 我们分析 从而了解发生了什么
so they get us the data and then we analyze it and determine what happened.
如果计算机某处出问题了
Something would go wrong in the computer,
传回来的时候还会混杂其他遥测系统的故障
and it always goes wrong when something else is messing up the telemetry system,
我们真正在做的 实际上他们叫八进制输出
so we would actually get what they call an octal dump.
我们用11x17英寸的纸（约A3纸大小）
We have this 11 by 17 sheet of paper,
把10比特的八进制数字 一共四个字符
10-bit octal numbers, so you'd have, there were four characters.
八进制的话数字是0-7
Zero to seven's as high as you go with octal arithmetic.
全印下来的话 我想想 大概每页应该是40行30列左右
So you got all these things, I think it was like, maybe 40 columns and 30 rows or something like that,
然后我们把所有数据全印出来
so we would get this thing printed out,
每页都全是数字 我们要找的错误数字就藏在这里某个地方
and all it's just numbers, well, the piece we're looking for is in a particular place down here.
而我们可以先把遥测数据丢失的地方打印出来
Well, the drop out is where we, you know, telemetry dropout, we would actually get this printed out
打印到11x7的折叠纸上 沿着走廊铺开
11 by 7 fanfold paper, spread it down this hallway,
然后跪下 趴地上
get down on your hands and knees,
事先弄一个模板 切出……
make a template, cut out the…
因为总有一些数据是永远不变的
you'll have a number of measurements that'll always be the same, you know,
就像一个螺栓一样 它永远不会变
like a bolt, it never changes,
所以我们知道哪些数字本该是多少
so we know what those number's oughta be.
把那个地方切出洞 然后一页页滑动 挨篇看“这页没问题！”
So we cut the holes out and slide it down page by page, "Oh, hey, these all look good!
“这帧看上去可能也没问题”
"Okay, this frame's probably good."
所以我们找了无数行 无数列 找到我们想要的数据 把它写下来
So we go find so many columns, so many rows, find the number we want, write it down.
所以您找的是
So you're looking for one
如果某个数碰巧是你想要的那个固定值
If it bungs up something that you know is a fixed value
那它周围就可能都是你想要的那个值
then it probably bunged up something else.
而且如果那个固定值找到了 那它附近的数据应该也没问题
That's right, and if the fixed value's okay, then somewhere in there our number's probably okay.
那当你找到那个 有问题的数据
And then once you've got the problematic one,
这不就是在做全世界最恶心的数独题吗？
I mean, is that just the world's nastiest sudoku puzzle?
你们怎么解决的？
How do you solve that?
呃……你得对比很多很多帧
Well, no, you may have, you may have to do this for many, many, many frames.
然后再回到桌上 拿着那些八进制数
Then you take it to your desk and take those octal numbers,
挨个转成十进制数
convert 'em to decimal numbers,
到校准表上一对比发现 “啊我找到那个数字了”
go to a calibration chart and say, "Okay, I got this number."
算完说这个意思是5摄氏度
Go up my chart and say that means it's five degrees Centigrade.
那就写下5摄氏度
So you write down five degrees,
然后找到你在哪一帧
then you figure out what frame you are,
就能推算出时间
and that's about what time it is,
所以就是“在某某某时间 得到数据是5摄氏度”
so you're, "At this time, I had five degrees."
然后你要找下一条数据
Then you go to the next one.
这个活要干上大概两个礼拜
Now you do this for about two weeks,
最后你会得到一幅手绘的图表
and finally you got enough to plot a graph by hand.
手工把一个个数据绘制在图表上 然后得出结论
So you put all these numbers in and you plot it by hand, and then you say,
“看来问题不是出在这里”
"Hm, that wasn't the problem after all.
“得 重来”
"Oh, well, here we go again."
这位是Ed 他是展览策划人
This is Ed. Ed is the head curator.
手里这个容器装有几个存储磁环
This is kind of an in-the-hand example of the memory cores
你能看到这边编织好后放大看大概是这样的
that you can see woven into the spread here and then kinda under the magnification over here,
我手里大概是有八九个磁环
and there's about eight or nine of them in there.
就像Luke刚说的 当你在中间通电流的时候
So like Luke was saying, when you run the current through there,
就会让环状物产生特定方向的磁场
it starts to spin that doughnut in a particular direction,
从而表示1或0
and that tells you whether it's the one or the zero.
你也说了 这些都是手工编织的 最初这活都是女士们做的
And you were saying they were woven on by hand, and it was primarily women that did the work,
每人都有一个工作台
that had basically a bench top.
所以我猜她们应该是有纺织工业的从业经验？
So they would have like textile industry experience, I guess.
呃……我并不了解她们的从业认证如何
Um, I am actually not certain what their qualifications were,
但她们的确会坐在工作台上 把这东西固定在面前
but they would sit with a bench top with this thing mounted in a holder
用手拿着镊子 穿那些铜线
with copper wire lengths and tweezers and their fingers
还要有比我强无数倍的耐心
and a lot more patience than I have,
把它们一个个正确的穿过磁环
to weave these things through there, to make sure they went through appropriately,
不能打结 不能有超出标准的弯曲
no kinks, no bends that were out of the spec,
保证小磁环穿在它们应该在的位置上
and to actually make sure that the little doughnuts go into across the way they should
而一切都是统一的 所以一切都是重复性的操作
and that it was all uniform so everything would be predictable behavior.
简直了
Incredible.
你可以把这些物理比特放在手里 感受一下它是什么样的
I just wanted you to hold the physical bit, now you know what that's like.
这已经超过8比特了 所以我手里的已经至少是一个字节了
I mean, this is, this is more than 8 bits, so I'm holding at least a byte.
所以Luke先生 您看到这个东西 您心里有怎样的想法？
So when you look at this, what kind of emotion do you feel, when you look at this, Luke?
您……您会感到自豪吗？
Do you, do you, are you proud?
是对它充满爱 还是默念“谢天谢地终于不用再碰这破玩意了”？
Is it fondness, or is it more just, "Thank goodness I don't have to work on that bloody thing any more"?
不 我会跟我朋友说好 等你们走出这栋楼的时候
No, I'm gonna talk to one of my buddies when you go out the building,
看他能不能来抢你们
see if he'd hit you in the head.
抢这个？
To get this thing?
对
Yeah.
呃……这真的是一款杰作
No, that's a real piece of work,
看上去好多来这里参观的人
and it looks, to people that come in here,
说这东西更像是一个古董
they say this just looks so much like an antique.
可是别忘了 这东西在所有飞行中只断断续续出现过几次故障
But again, we only had a few failures during the whole flight that were intermittent.
我们从来没出过灾难性的故障
We never had a catastrophic failure.
人们可能说它古董 但我要说它是纯手工的杰作
People might say antique, but I would say hand-crafted.
真的 这需要很多人的巧手才能造就这个作品
Yes, it was a lot of hand work went into these.
噢 能看出来 这里好多地方都是手工烧上去的
Oh, you can tell, I mean, even just, even these are clearly hand-baked.
他们会涂上这些像口香糖一样的胶 因为这东西怕的是震动
Well, they got the goop on 'em because the big problem with this thing is vibration.
我们看到的那些存储模块……
The memory that we were looking at over there --
是啊 上面挂着那些小磁环呢
Yeah, you got physical rings on there.
他们反反复复测试过存储模块
They test and test and test on that thing
保证线不会出现打结或扭曲
to make sure that you hadn't got a kink in a wire or a twist,
因为如果有了 那震动就会让它损坏
'cause if you do, the vibration's gonna cause it to break.
这些东西都是手工打造的
Those things were made by hand.
女士们编织这些东西的时候就像在织一块布
The ladies actually wove these things like you're weaving a piece of cloth.
真的很厉害
Pretty amazing.
太有意思了
Oh, this is fascinating.
非常感谢您！
Thank you very much, by the way.
欢迎前往老莱的频道 Linus Tech Tips
Go check out Linus's channel, Linus Tech Tips.
他要讲讲……讲啥来着？
He's talking about, what's it called again?
控制设备单元 我们聊了一点计算机的内容
The instrument unit, basically we talk a little bit about the computer
但Destin这方面懂得多一点
but Destin's got a little more information on that,
而我真的很喜欢这东西上的冷却系统
but I really love the cooling system on this thing,
震撼你妈一整年
it's gonna blow your guys's mind. Unreal.
真的很牛逼 控制设备单元在火箭顶部
It's awesome, it's at the top of the rocket
因为土星五号有三级 你需要控制设备单元一直呆在火箭上
because as you got all three stages of the Saturn V, you need your instrument unit way up here
才能在阿波罗飞船计算机接管控制之前让土星五号有制导功能
so you can guide the Saturn V before the Apollo computer takes over,
而老莱会讲讲电源的细节 和它的工作原理
but Linus talks about details of power and how that stuff works.
不错哦
It's pretty cool.
Yeah.
谢啦老铁
Thanks, dude, appreciate it.
拜拜了
See you guys.
多谢
Thank you.
你们太帅啦~
You're welcome!
谢谢同学们~
Thanks, guys!
这叫航天夏令营
It's called space camp.
航天夏令营
Space camp.
对 一帮孩子来这学习怎么才能当宇航员 当战机飞行员
Yeah, so all those kids are here to learn how to be astronauts and fighter pilots.
这就是Luke
That's Luke.
不会吧！
No!
这真是Luke
That's Luke.
天啊
No way!
左边那位
On the left there, apparently.
老帅了是吧
That's pretty cool, huh?
这写着呢 Luke Talley 最左边
Luke Talley, there it is, far left.
牛逼
That's nice.